Guide to the Frances Bernice Field Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frances Bernice Field papers
1946-1975
MS 744
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(6 boxes)
Correspondence, drafts of speeches, articles, reports, and printed and typed material related to cataloguing. The papers are related exclusively to Field's professional life as a librarian and cataloguer, and is mostly composed of printed or other duplicated material.
Field, Frances Bernice, 1906-1974
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of F. Bernice Field, and of the Technical Services Department of Sterling Memorial Library, 1974.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Frances Bernice Field consist of correspondence, drafts of speeches, articles, reports, and printed matter related to Field's profession as a librarian and cataloguer. The material is arranged in subject files alphabetically by organization; the folder headings for the most part are those used by Field. Indication of the type of material, whether correspondence, reports, writings by Field, and so forth, has been added. Three boxes are devoted to the American Library Association, and in particular to the Descriptive Cataloging Committee, of which Field was chairman from 1960-1966, and to the revision of Rules for Descriptive Cataloging undertaken by that committee. A fourth box contains materials relating to Yale University and to the Yale Library; the remaining two boxes contain papers relating to Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, in the revision of which Field was active, to the Joint Committee on the Union List of Serials, Inc., and to other professional organizations. There is a small group of general materials (Box 1) not directly related to the various organizations; these include letters of congratulations on Field's receipt of the Mann Citation for outstanding professional achivement in cataloging (1966), letters of recommendation written by her, letters offering jobs to her, and a small number of personal letters. There are also newspaper clippings, resumés, obituaries, and other memorabilia.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Frances Bernice Field: president of New York Technical Services Librarians, 1953-1954; appointed Head of Yale University Cataloguing Department, 1955; became Associate Librarian for Technical Services in 1965; recipient of Margaret Mann citation of the American Library Association, 1966.
Libraries; Librarians; Field, Frances Bernice, 1906-1974; Yale University -- Officals and employees
- Inventory, 1946-1975
  - General
    - Correspondence, 1947-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
    - Resumés, obituaries, clippings, memorabilia, 1955-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Library Association
    - General correspondence, 1952-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Descriptive Cataloging Committee
      - General correspondence and memoranda, 1947-1966 (Box 1, Folder 12-18)
      - Minutes and annual reports, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Non-book materials: correspondence and other papers, 1953-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
      - Transliteration: correspondence and other papers, 1958-1965 (Box 1, Folder 23-29)
    - Personnel clinic, 1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Publications committees, 1964-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
    - Resources and Technical Services Division
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1956-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 34-39)
      - Minutes and conference materials, 1955-1967 (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
      - Writings by F.B. Field, 1959-1967 (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
    - Rules for Descriptive Cataloging
      - General correspondence and memoranda, 1962-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
      - Chapter 3: correspondence and memoranda, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 46-48)
      - Chapters 4-7: correspondence and memoranda, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Chapter 7: revisions, Undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Chapters 8-11: correspondence and memoranda, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Chapters 8, 10: revisions, 1962-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - Appendices: correspondence and memoranda, 1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - Limited cataloging: correspondence and memoranda, 1948, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 54-59)
    - Serials: writings, 1956, undated (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
    - Serials Committee
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1948-1953 (Box 3, Folder 62-63)
      - Minutes, reports, etc., 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Serials Round Table
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1949-1956 (Box 3, Folder 65-70)
      - Minutes, reports, etc., 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Serials Subcommittee
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1947-1948, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 72-75)
      - Reports, writings, etc., 1947-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 76-77)
  - Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 78-83)
    - American Theological Library Association Conference materials, 1967 June (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Workshop on the Anglo-American Cataloguing Code materials, 1967 April (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Writings by F.B. Field, 1966-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 86-87)
    - Helen Hadley Hall Fellows
      - Correspondence and minutes, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 88-89)
      - Financial papers, 1970-1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 90-91)
  - Joint Committee on the Union List of Serials, Inc.
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1956-1966 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Minutes, agendas, etc., 1957-1962 (Box 4, Folder 93-94)
    - Reports and writings, 1957-1966 (Box 4, Folder 95-97)
  - The Library Association
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1961-1968, undated (Box 5, Folder 98-100)
    - Minutes, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 101-102)
  - New England Library Information Network: correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Yale University Council on Priorities and Planning
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1969-1974 (Box 5, Folder 104-105)
    - Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 106-107)
    - Reports, 1964-1973 (Box 5, Folder 108-109)
  - Yale University Library
    - Selective Book Retirement Program
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1960-1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 110)
      - Education: notes and printed matter, 1950-1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 111-112)
      - Reports, 1961-1964, undated (Box 6, Folder 113-116)
    - Serials Department
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1947-1974 (Box 6, Folder 117-118)
      - Annual reports, 1946-1952 (Box 6, Folder 119-121)
      - Serial cataloging manual, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 122-124)
    - Other organizations: correspondence, memorabilia, 1949-1970 (Box 6, Folder 125-126)